{"tossups": [{"question": "<b><u>This scientist disputed Christoph Scheiner's claims in the</u> </b><em><b><u>Apelles</u></b></em><b><u> letters by</u></b> <b><u>claiming his observations took place first in the</u> </b><em><b><u>Letters on Sunspots</u></b></em><b><u>. This man may have</u></b> <b><u>depicted (+)</u> Pope Urban VIII as the dimwitted \"Simplicio\" in his </b><em><b>Dialogue Concerning </b><b>the Two Chief World Systems</b></em><b>, and was widely held to have muttered \"And yet it (*) </b>moves\" after publicly recanting his theories. For ten points, name this Italian scientist who was found guilty of heresy for promoting heliocentrism.", "answer": "<b><u>Galileo</u><u>Galilei</u></b> (or <b><u>Galileo</u></b> di Vincenzo Bonaiuti de' <b><u>Galilei</u></b>; accept either underlined portion)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Shortly after a petition presaging this movement was adopted at the Sign of the</u></b> <b><u>Green Tree Tavern, its supporters attacked Robin Johnson at Pigeon Creek. A satire</u></b> <b><u>about \"Jersey (+)</u> Blue\" militiamen is the origin for the nickname of the force that put down this movement, the Watermelon Army. President Washington (*) </b>rode out to personally supervise this rebellion's suppression. For ten points, name this early 1790s revolt in Western Pennsylvania that arose after a federal excise tax was placed on liquor.", "answer": "<b><u>Whiskey</u></b> Rebellion (accept \"Revolt\" or \"Insurrection\" for \"Rebellion\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This man repeated the exhortation \"let them come\" to the location of a speech</u></b> <b><u>four times, after outlining groups such as those who \"don't understand...what is the</u></b> <b><u>great issue.\" This orator posited that \"today, in the (+)</u> world of freedom,\" a new phrase is the equivalent of the ancient \"civis Romanus sum.\" This man stated \"you live in a defended island of freedom\" and included a phrase which a later myth falsely claimed was confused for a claim to be a (*) </b>jelly doughnut. For ten points, the \"Ich bin ein Berliner\" speech was given in West Berlin by what U.S. President?", "answer": "<b><u>J</u></b>ohn F(itzgerald) <b><u>Kennedy</u></b>, Sr. (accept <b><u>JFK</u></b>; prompt on \"Kennedy\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>An 18.4 cent federal tax on a commonly sold commodity unit creates the \"trust</u></b> <b><u>fund\" named for these things. E.J. Mehring promoted the expansion of these things,</u></b> <b><u>which are depicted on the Pershing (+)</u> Map. A threat to withhold federal funding for these things was used to implement the nationwide 21-year-old drinking age in the (*) </b>1980s. For ten points, name these public goods that, after seeing the German Autobahn, Dwight Eisenhower promoted as part of an \"interstate\" system.", "answer": "<b><u>Highway</u></b>s (accept Interstate <b><u>highway</u></b>s; prompt on \"roads\"; prompt on \"Interstate(s)\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This city was embroiled in several lawsuits over the failure to build ramps</u></b> <b><u>connecting its streets to major bridges in the Gateway Project. An attempt to build a</u></b> <b><u>new (+)</u> bridge out of this American city was long opposed by Manuel Moroun, who privately owned another bridge from this city that comprises the busiest U.S.-Canada (*) </b>border crossing. For ten points, name this American city on one end of bridges named MacArthur, Ambassador, and Gordie Howe, also known for being the headquarters of Chrysler, GM, and Ford.", "answer": "<b><u>Detroit</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Actor Peter Falk was recruited by this country\u2019s government to tell its citizens</u></b> <b><u>that the government was not hoarding episodes of the TV show</u> </b><em><b><u>Columbo</u></b></em><b><u>. One leader of</u></b> <b><u>this country outlined his ideas in the \u201cJuly (+)</u> Theses\u201d and banned contraception and abortion with Decree 770. This country was the only Warsaw Pact member that did not boycott the 1984 Summer (*) </b>Olympics. For ten points, name this nation whose dictator, Nicolae Ceau\u0219escu [[chow-SHESS-koo]] was executed on Christmas Day, 1989.", "answer": "<b><u>Romania</u></b> (accept Socialist Republic of <b><u>Romania</u></b>; or Republica Socialist\u0103  <b><u>Rom\u00e2nia</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This man joined the Artaman League youth group, part of the V\u00f6lkisch [[FUHL-</u><u>kish]] movement, which influenced this leader to found the Ahnerbe [[AHN-ehr-buh]]</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> occult research center. This man, who appointed Reinhard Heydrich [[HAI-drik]] to one position, organized the Einsatzgruppen [[INE-zats-GROO-pen]] death squads and ordered the expansion of sites like (*) </b>Treblinka and Auschwitz. For ten points, name this leader of the Nazi SS and primary architect of the Holocaust.", "answer": "Heinrich <b><u>Himmler</u></b> (or Heinrich Luitpold <b><u>Himmler</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Zhang Zeduan [[ZEH-DWAHN]] was patronized by this dynasty\u2019s royal family to</u></b> <b><u>paint landscapes in the</u> </b><em><b><u>shan shui</u></b></em><b><u> style. This dynasty (+)</u> outfitted its warships with a traction trebuchet which launched early explosives, proving vital during the Battle of Caishi [[KYE-SHEE]] on the Yangtze River. The encroachment of the \u201cGreat Jin,\u201d a rival power composed of a Jurchen noble class, led to this dynasty\u2019s \u201cSouthern\u201d period. The Mongol (*) </b>Yuan Dynasty overthrew, for ten points, which Chinese dynasty which ruled from the 10th to 13th century?", "answer": "<b><u>Song</u></b> Dynasty (or <b><u>S\u00f2ng</u></b> ch\u00e1o; accept Southern or Northern <b><u>Song</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>46 years after the northern part of this people's territory was invaded by the</u></b> <b><u>Rus under Sviatoslov, Nikephoros Xiphias engineered a major defeat of this people</u></b> <b><u>following the end of the (+)</u> Krum dynasty. This people's Tsar Samuel died two months after the disastrous Battle of Kleidion, where 99% of their surviving soldiers were (*) </b>blinded. For ten points, name this Balkan people whose army was destroyed by Byzantine emperor Basil II, who became known as the \"slayer\" of them.", "answer": "<b><u>Bulgar</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Bulgar</u></b>ians)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>A revolt against a holder of this title began after the queen Kassi was isolated</u></b> <b><u>and targeted a man who hosted Ibn Battuta. A holder of this title named Mohammed</u></b> <b><u>ibn (+)</u> Gao was said to have disappeared while attempting to sail across the Atlantic Ocean. The first holder of this title, who won the Battle of Kirina against Sumanguru, was Sundiata Keita. Later holders of this title reigned from (*) </b>Timbuktu. For ten points, give this title for the emperors of Mali, which was held in the early 14th century by Musa I.", "answer": "<b><u>Mansa</u></b> (accept <b><u>Mansa</u></b> Musa; or <b><u>Mansa</u></b> Sundiata Keita; <b><u>Mansa</u></b> Mohammed Ibn Gao)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}